hey folks David Tao with barbin.com and
we're bringing you coverage of day four
of the 2023 Noble CrossFit Games by the
way it can get a little
gay four but four but it's only day two
of individual and team competition and
that's because the Adaptive and age
group divisions competed on the first
three days of competition including
Tuesday and Wednesday when they competed
without the individuals and teams we've
got full Recaps of those linked below
and at barbad.com but today we're going
to break down who is in moving position
who's in trouble as well as specific
event Recaps so we're first going to
give a recap of the leaderboards for men
women and teams and then we're going to
break it down event by event at the end
we'll give a little color commentary as
well as what we think you should be
watching for heading into the weekend
after all Saturday is moving day also
want to say if you're not already
subscribed to barbin on YouTube go ahead
and smash that subscribe button do they
still say that smash that subscribe
button I'm too old for that anyway go
ahead and subscribe to stay up to date
on all things CrossFit strongman
weightlifting powerlifting bodybuilding
and more you're already watching YouTube
it's really easy it's like one button
just go ahead and do it something that
gets a little confusing and something I
want to note right now is that watching
the CrossFit Games got a little more
complicated this year during the games
CrossFit actually announced a new
streaming contract with ESPN which means
that the entirety of the games will not
necessarily be streamed live on YouTube
at least not for folks in the United
States turns out there'll be some blocks
of time when you'll need to watch on
ESPN2 or ESPN plus basically you'll need
to be an ESPN subscriber we have more
details on that and are updated how to
watch article which we've linked below
you can also find that at barbad.com it
just kind of threw a wrench into some
folks viewing plans this weekend
certainly ours but if you're an ESPN
subscriber it should be no issue it is
also kind of nice to see the CrossFit
Games back on TV I guess one other thing
to note there was a big withdrawal on
the individual side Ireland's Fitness
woman Emma McQuaid she had to withdraw
due to injury today and we really hate
to see her go this year Emma's actually
a friend of the brand she's been on our
podcast so wishing you a speedy recovery
Emma all right let's talk about the
leaderboard on the men's side krenikov
is currently in first place overall
taking a fair highly commanding lead
heading into Saturday don't call it a
comeback he's been here for years
Chandler Smith of the United States
seems like Chandler's been knocking on
the door of CrossFit greatness for a
long time in the late 20 teens he kind
of burst onto the regional scenes had
some games qualifications but was never
able to really knock on the door of the
podium turns out this year he might be
doing just that he's an athlete who has
had a couple weaknesses in his game over
the years but looks to have shorn up a
lot of those and hey he's certainly
sitting in second place right now so
Chandler's a fan favorite he's actually
active on the CrossFit subreddit he's
also just a really nice guy and kind of
a people's champ in a lot of folks
Hearts already so good to see him really
living up to clearly a ton of Fitness
that he's built over the years and he
seems to be having a lot of fun doing it
so I just can't call that out enough how
much the people are cheering for
Chandler Smith Jeffrey Adler of Canada
again Adler is another one of those
athletes he's kind of always knocking on
the door of the podium is placing
himself in really good position heading
into Saturday rounding out the top five
on the men's side we have Jay Crouch of
Australia and a familiar name Brent
fakowski the professor from Canada a
name you're not going to see in the top
five right now is two-time defending
CrossFit Games Champion Justin madiros
who currently sits in 16th Place overall
now he had his worst game start ever in
the first two events that occurred on
Thursday he started battling back but
had another disappointing finish
finishing in 30th on the sixth event of
the games which was the final event on
Friday so Maderos has an uphill battle
and it's already begun to seem like that
leader Jersey is slipping away and from
my position right now and from my
perspective seemingly unlikely that he
can repeat this year but hey stranger
things have happened let's talk about
the women's side currently sitting in
first place but not by a huge margin is
Emma Lawson of Canada Alexis raptis of
the United States currently sits in
second place and Laura Horvath who was
the odds on favorite for the women's
field coming into this game sits in
third place overall although she's
making up quite a bit of ground it seems
and clearly has a competitor's mentality
and maybe even a Winner's mentality
heading into Saturday it's kind of weird
if you were watching the games you would
think that Horvath was in first place
for most of the day even though she
wasn't wearing the leaders jersey but
that's just how tenaciously she's been
attacking these workouts she clearly
wants to break through and not only make
the podium again but take home a
championship but Lawson and raptis are
really showcasing their Fitness and
they're proving tough competitors to
beat so horror bath is going to need to
continue to perform very well hit some
workouts she's really strong and hope
that raptis and loss and Do Slip there
might be a chance for horror bath to
regain some ground or to gain some new
ground tomorrow and I'm going to talk
about that toward the end of this
broadcast rounding out the top five two
Americans Alex gazan and Arielle lowen
those are your top five competitors
heading into Saturday nipping at their
heels I just want to point out still
relevant to the conversation a personal
favorite of mine someone I've known for
a long time and that's Iceland's own
Annie thorstadter who is competing in
her like a 70 billionth CrossFit Games I
mean she started this in 2009. let's
talk about the fourth event overall the
First on Friday for the individuals and
that's called alpaca Redux it involves
some really heavy sled pushes legless
rope climbs and kettlebell clean and
jerks oh kettlebells okay you have my
interest
it was a really grueling workout and
something that challenged a lot of
athletes when it came to positioning and
technique and strategy especially on the
sled pushes literally some athletes were
coming out of their shoes on the turf
that's how intensely heavy and demanding
these pushes were as far as winners go
karenikov won this event by about 20
second on the men's side on the women's
side Emma tall who's known for her
strength and can really brute force a
sled apparently as we saw she gets her
first ever career games win on this
event a few other names I want to note
moderos showed Signs of Life finishing
in the top 10 on this event and Laura
Horvath finished in second on the
women's side which really helped
catapult her up the leaderboard let's
talk about the second event of the day
and the fifth overall for the
individuals ski bag that's a weird name
anyway it involves calories on the
skierg and heavy sandbag squats these
were not light sandbag squats they were
heavy 200 pounds for the men 125 pounds
for the women have you picked up 125
pound sandbag I have it's really heavy
it's really awkward it's tough to do
basically anything and the athletes had
to squat with it in between rounds of
calories on the ski org this is an event
that was more challenging on the core
than I think a lot of people anticipated
and it's a combination that I don't know
if a lot of folks had practiced I mean
probably not they're like infinite
movements in CrossFit but this is one
that trust me will leave your core
smoked if you try it at home so proceed
with caution and maybe use lighter
sandbags than these Elite athletes at
least on your first go on the men's side
Colton Mertens won his first career
CrossFit Games event and guess who won
on the women's side someone who's really
fit good at monostructural movements
who's really strong and can move awkward
weights for a bunch of reps oh yeah
Laura Horvath she wins her eighth career
CrossFit Games event and again further
cemented herself or at least positioned
herself on the leaderboard heading into
Saturday this is a big moving event for
Horvath and one where she gained a lot
of momentum and energy from the crowd
and Spectators the third and final event
of the day and the sixth overall for the
individuals was Helena which was a Twist
on the classic CrossFit Benchmark
workout Helen it involved a run bar
muscle ups and moderately heavy dumbbell
snatches this actually looks like a fun
one and one that I might try at a track
near me I might regret saying that on
the men's side Jeffrey Adler of Canada
was the only athlete in the entire field
to finish this workout under eight
minutes so he won on the women's side
Jamie Simmons takes the win and Laura
Horvath actually finished in 15th Place
which again doesn't spell defeat for her
in any way like I said she built a lot
of momentum heading into the day but she
probably didn't finish the day like she
had hoped and this was certainly her
worst performance on Friday before we
get into teams I want to talk about Cuts
CrossFit has said that after the end of
Friday's competition the top 30 men and
top 30 women will advance which means
that about 10 athletes in each of those
divisions won't advance so that's
something to keep in mind we're going to
have smaller fields and fewer Heats
heading into the weekend a couple names
that won't be joining the athletes over
the weekend because they didn't make the
cut well two on the men's side Jason
Hopper and appearing in his final
CrossFit Games as an individual or so he
says Cole Steger after nearly or
actually almost exactly a decade at The
toppest rung of the sport Cole Sager has
contributed a lot to the sport he's
still going to be contributing a lot as
a coach and Mentor heck he's been on our
podcast and it was one of my favorite
ever episodes to record so Cole thanks
for all you've done and kind of wish
we'd seen you compete over the weekend
but them's the breaks or the cuts
literally let's talk about the team's
leaderboard and it's no different than
it was at the end of day one of their
competition which was actually day three
as I described earlier in the video it
gets confusing anyway basically the
leaderboard hasn't changed Crossfit
Invictus is at the top CrossFit Oslo
navy blue is in second and Crossfit East
Nashville proven still sits in third
place overall teams had three events on
the day the there was an Olympic total
there was the cross country run and a
bike row hold event and I want to narrow
in on or zoom in on narrowing on that
doesn't make any sense I want to zoom in
on one of those events because it's
relevant for the athletes on the
individual side tomorrow so at the time
of this recording we know two of the
events tomorrow for the individuals
there's a 5K and the athletes will run
five kilometers that one's pretty
self-explanatory I haven't done one of
those in a while personally no one needs
to hear that there's also an Olympic
weightlifting total where athletes will
look for Maxes in the snatch and the
clean and jerk that one is one I'm
particularly excited about we love
seeing these athletes lift heavyweight
that's also one where we see athletes
pushing themselves and I hate to bring
it up but I'm a little
well I'm gonna be watching with baited
breath because I was there live in 2021
when Brooke Wells uh dislocated her
elbow on a Mac snatch ladder these are
always events that are exciting but they
can also result in injury as these
athletes have a lot of wear and tear on
their bodies and have a lot of stress
that has accrued over the course of
these events I'm a little surprised
CrossFit didn't put this earlier in the
week personally that's just my opinion
though I think starting with something
like this might make a little more sense
as opposed to after these athletes have
had a lot of running and biking and
gymnastics under their belts one thing
to note Ben Smith competing on the team
side it seems like he suffered a small
patella tear during the Olympic
weightlifting portion of the team event
but so far it seems like he's going to
continue to try and compete so wishing
him a speedy recovery even though he
technically hasn't withdrawn from
competition yet Ben is a former Fitness
man on Earth and a tenacious competitor
so I'm not super surprised and hope
there's no long-term damage there anyway
people love watching these athletes lift
big weights and comparing what they can
lift two Elite Olympic weightlifters and
well we'll have some more data points
tomorrow after that event a couple
things to look out for tomorrow Justin
Maderos what's going on with him and
though he survived a cut he's certainly
not sitting in an ideal position heading
into the weekend the question isn't will
Justin Maderos repeat I think it's
almost impossible for him to do so at
this point even if he has been
mathematically crunched out of the
numbers the question is can he really
make a shot at the top 10 or top five
he's been very inconsistent and had his
worst game finishes ever this weekend so
I'm not sure exactly what's going on I
don't want to wish Justin ill at all
Justin's fantastic he's been a fantastic
Ambassador and Champion for the sport
but clearly the pieces haven't quite
stacked together how he wanted this
weekend Laura Horvath finds herself in
Podium position and it seems like some
of her weaker events are already behind
her including the inverted medley one
where no one really expected her to
perform that well and she didn't really
perform that well but we've got a run
coming up I expect her to do pretty well
there and we have an Olympic lifting
total coming up I expect her to do quite
well there although I'm not sure she
will really
take it uh it's very difficult to
predict who is going to lift what we see
PR's come out of nowhere in these events
so I'm not going to say this person is
going to win I don't necessarily want to
predict that but I know Laura Horvath or
I predict Laura Horvath will do well
there Emma Lawson and Alexis raptis I
think they might lose some ground to
Laura Horvath in that event although
with the 5K as well uh there's a lot to
be seen we'll have to tune in to find
out either way we like seeing big
weights go up that's what we're gonna
see so there you have it two of
competition down for the individuals and
teams some surprises uh only a couple
big names really gone after the cuts
heading into the weekend and a lot of
action left to come until then I'm David
Tao thanks for tuning in
[Music]